<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Current Work | Timo Haber</title>
    <link>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Current Work</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://timohaber.github.io/media/icon_hu0705edf470ad0aef9c6699815b1d2148_4384_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Current Work</title>
      <link>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financial Constraints and Firm Size: Micro-Evidence and Aggregate Implications (Submitted)</title>
      <link>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/ferreira_haber_roerig/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/ferreira_haber_roerig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using a unique dataset covering the universe of Portuguese firms, their credit situation, and bank relationship we show that firms across the entire size distribution exhibit a positive elasticity of loans and capital to credit supply shocks. This finding is counterfactual to basic theory that posits large firms as unconstrained and not reacting to credit supply shocks. Incorporating a richer, empirically supported, productivity process into a standard heterogeneous firms model generates large constrained firms and consequently a joint distribution of size and credit elasticities in line with the data. The elevated capital share and sensitivity to financial shocks of the largest decile of constrained firms explains about onethird of the response of output to a financial shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/miguelhferreira/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Miguel H. Ferreira&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://timohaber.github.io/&#34;&gt;Timo Haber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://christianroerig.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Christian Rörig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monopolistically Skewed Business Cycles</title>
      <link>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/bennhoff_haber_schmitz/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/bennhoff_haber_schmitz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We show that the cross-sectional distribution of firm growth rates changes shape over the business cycle: it is right-skewed in booms, left-skewed in recessions, and these swings are more pronounced for larger firms. We call this the size gradient of skewness. We show that one way of explaining this pattern is through a parsimonious demand-side framework in which market power maps symmetric shocks into skewed growth outcomes. Stronger market power implies more concave responses and thus greater skewness. Countercyclical variance - or equivalently heterogeneous exposures to aggregate impulses - then generates the procyclical, size-dependent skewness we observe. Consistent with this mechanism, impulse responses to aggregate shocks show that growth and skewness move in tandem, with the skewness response concentrated among large firms. The results imply that large firms amplify cyclical asymmetry through market power, and that outcome-based policies risk responding to distributional patterns that reflect propagation rather than the shocks themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://fredhb.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Frederik Bennhoff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://timohaber.github.io/&#34;&gt;Timo Haber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.schmitzniklas.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Niklas Schmitz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Inefficient Corporate Cash Buffer and the Nonlinear Business Cycle</title>
      <link>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/ferreira_haber_lee2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/ferreira_haber_lee2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper studies the macroeconomic implications of corporate cash holdings over the business cycle. We develop a heterogeneous firm business cycle model in which firms accumulate cash for precautionary reasons. Firm-level cash accumulation is highly nonlinear due to a satiation point. This nonlinearity survives aggregation, shaping the aggregate allocations’ state-dependent responsiveness to TFP shocks. In periods of high cash holdings, firms can smooth dividend payouts, thereby dampening the response of aggregate consumption to adverse TFP shocks. Despite this stabilizing role, we show that the decentralized equilibrium level of cash holdings is inefficiently high due to a negative cash externality. We conclude by providing micro-level empirical evidence in support of the model’s key mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/miguelhferreira/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Miguel H. Ferreira&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://timohaber.github.io/&#34;&gt;Timo Haber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/sas.upenn.edu/hanbaeklee/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hanbaek Lee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Premia to Spirals: How Financial Frictions Drive Lumpy Investments</title>
      <link>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/ferreira_haber_lee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://timohaber.github.io/current_work/ferreira_haber_lee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/miguelhferreira/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Miguel H. Ferreira&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://timohaber.github.io/&#34;&gt;Timo Haber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/sas.upenn.edu/hanbaeklee/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hanbaek Lee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
